Downloaded from
YTS.MX
Official YIFY movies site:
[**]
[CHANTING]
[SIGHS]
Ma! Señora Nunez came in.
She's burning up with fever.
Go cool her head.
Recite the 23rd Psalm.
I'll be there in a bit.
New Mexico, 1885
"Though I walk through the
valley of the shadow of death,
I fear no evil."
Morning, kids.
"Thou art with me.
Thy rod and staff...
[SPEAKS SPANISH]
"...they comfort me.
"Thou preparest a table
before me
"in the presence
of mine enemies.
"Thou anointest my head with
oil. My cup runneth over.
[SPEAKS SPANISH]
"Surely goodness and mercy
"shall follow me
all the days of my life.
"And I will dwell
in the house--
Darling,
get me some Cocea paste
and my tooth plier, please.
Yes, ma'am.
[SPEAKING SPANISH]
No. No.
[CONVERSING IN SPANISH]
She don't worry
about the pain. No.
It is her only tooth.
She worry how she look.
Thank you.
[SPEAKS SPANISH]
No! No, no!
I gonna need you to hold
your grandmother down.
Darling, can you
hold her arm?
Pin that, Dot. Hold her nose.
Hold her nose.
[SPANISH CONTINUES]
Careful.
[SCREAMING]
Gracias.
[OLD WOMAN GROANING]
I hate to ask...
but can you
pay me for this today?
[CURSES IN SPANISH]
[ANIMAL SCREAMS]
[GUNSHOT]
[WHIMPERING]
[GUN COCKS]
Jumping pinches coyotes
sons of bitches.
That lightning sure did
kill her.
[COW MOOS]
[HORSE WHINNIES]
This calf ain't gonna
last the night out here.
Let's put her in the barn.
Señor Brake.
Indian.
Apache, maybe.
Some kind of Apache
son of a bitch.
[**]
BRAKE: Good day, sir.
I said, hello.
That your man over there
in the trees?
What is he planning on doing
with that carbine?
We've had trouble
with coyotes killing calves.
Tell him I'm not a coyote.
[WHISTLES]
Is that the healer's place?
BRAKE: You come for doctoring?
[COWS MOOING]
BRAKE: Lady shuts her doors
at sundown.
She's pretty firm
about her hours.
You're welcome
to spend the night,
see her in the morning,
though.
I thank you kindly.
Barn's this way, mister.
There's a spare bunk
over there, Mr...
Mr. Fernandez.
Jones. The man that owned
that saddle tried to kill me.
I was living with
the Jicarilla at the time.
I suppose he thought
I was one of them.
You're Apache, huh?
[MUTTERS IN SPANISH]
What did you say?
Forget it.
[SPEAKS SPANISH]
[REPLIES IN SPANISH]
Come over here.
Now, I mean it!
There'll be no trouble here.
If that's too tough for you to
understand, you can move on.
[HORSE SNORTS]
Emiliano, unpack his mule.
You will keep your hands
off of my mule...
Emiliano.
[DOOR OPENS]
Don't slam that door.
BRAKE: Yes, ma'am.
You know there are houses
in Cleveland
with lamps that run
on electricity.
I'd like to see Cleveland.
Can you fetch the water,
please, Dot?
DOT: Yes, ma'am.
At the fair, there's gonna be
expositions of the future.
There's gonna be
a graphophone.
You can hear
your own voice back on it.
The Dickersons are going.
Brake can't spare you.
Ma.
Not tomorrow
with the cows calving.
The Fosters too.
Got all the future
you need right here.
Riding all day with this
cramping and all.
Don't you ever act
helpless and pitiable
to win favor with a man.
Some people shouldn't give
advice on how to act with men.
And it's "pitiful," not
"pitiable" in English.
You heard what I said.
That pail's half-empty.
I didn't do it.
It's that old Indian's
dumb old mule.
What Indian?
Some drifter
looking for doctoring.
If you're gonna eat
barefoot...
why don't you take supper
with the animals in the barn.
My boots don't fit no more.
Cut off my blood circulation.
It's your birthday soon.
I'll have gangrene by then.
Your mother may just have to
saw off your feet, then.
Like poor old Mr. Swenson.
[LAUGHING]
Mr. Jones.
Maggie, this is the visiting
gentleman I mentioned.
I'll bet a warm meal
sounds pretty good to you.
Magdalena.
I'm afraid we have
just enough food for family.
We can't be offering
our hospitality tonight.
I'm sure we can all do with
a little less on out plate.
MAGGIE: I'm quite sure
we can't!
I have two growing girls
to feed.
Maggie?
Maggie.
Lilly,
why don't you say grace.
Who is he?
Called you Magdalena.
Your hair bristles
when you lay eyes on him.
He scares me, is all.
Nobody scares you.
Can't trust him.
Maggie, who is he?
He's my father.
I thought your father
was dead.
He is.
To me, he is.
I want him gone, Brake.
You want him gone?
He's your kin.
You just can't--
He ran off when I wasn't
Dot's age. Went Indian.
Turn your back, he'll eat
your horses and dogs.
He's being chased...
or running from something,
I don't know what.
But he's bad, Brake.
I swear.
I do not want him
near my children.
We're Indians, Lilly.
We're Indians.
[SNORING]
Does he do that all night?
Oh, he's just getting started.
You come here for the healing?
In a manner of speaking.
Thought you might be hungry.
It's rabbit stew.
I can't eat rabbits.
I was bitten by a rattlesnake.
All right.
When there's company,
you sleep in there.
Is that right?
That's right.
You're not her husband?
No, sir.
Not for lack of asking.
They your children?
No.
What happened
to their father?
You don't know this?
I can't say what all
happened between you two...
but you ain't
welcome here, sir.
[SIGHS]
But she's a good Christian.
Hm.
She won't turn away
any man in need.
Tomorrow, she'll give you
what doctoring she can...
then you're on your way.
There are some places where a
father would kill a young man
for doing what you're doing,
you know that, don't you?
[DOOR CLOSES]
[SPEAKING IN APACHE]
If you have something to say,
say it.
Are you really a Indian?
Brake said you rode
with the Chiricahua.
That's right.
So that means
I'm part Indian, right?
No.
Not at all.
You look stupid
trying to work
in those fancy clothes,
you know.
I am leaving here
as soon as I can.
I'm moving to the city.
But Grandpa's visiting.
Did you see him?
He's a savage.
They're gut-eaters, you know.
I was born into
the wrong family,
I swear to God I was.
[DOOR OPENS]
I appreciate this.
Take off your shirt.
Magdalena--
Don't call me that.
It's not my name.
Where's it hurt?
Hurts when I breathe.
Mostly around here.
Yeah.
Your muscles are torn
just under your ribs.
You need to put
a cottonwood plaster to it.
You'll live.
I never thought you'd
turn out to be a healer.
I remember you had
that yellow cat one time.
You're crying because
a badger bit its tail off.
Don't remember.
Your mother came running--
Not in front of me.
Because I remember my mother.
My mother died
scrubbing a man's floor.
And you killed her.
Didn't shoot her or stab her,
but what you did...
You broke her!
And I remember my brother too.
He lasted six years.
I bet you never even
knew his name.
And I remember praying hard
every night
that you'd come home.
But on the day I put him
in the ground
I remember praying even harder
you were dead.
So you don't want to reminisce
with me, that I promise you.
I earned this money
in large part
killing mountain lions
for ranchers like you.
I want you to have it.
If I were destitute
and drawing my last breath--
This is good money.
You take this money
for your children.
No! You take it
for your funeral.
Magdalena...
I've done my duty
as a Christian.
You get the hell off my ranch!
[EMILIANO SPEAKS SPANISH]
[GUNSHOT]
I'd stop now.
[GUN COCKS]
Maggie asked you to leave.
I think it's time
you did so, sir.
Right about now.
[**]
So long.
Nice making your acquaintance.
What's done is done, I guess.
I know you would have
done different.
I appreciate
your regard, Brake.
I do.
Well, night, then.
Did they see you come in?
We can't make a sound.
Figure we can get them
all branded in a day?
You want Dot to stay
for company?
Brake, you said I could go.
You promised.
Mama, you promised too.
Oh, I'm fine.
He won't be coming back.
This will help
the cramping.
The calves are
a lot more important
than hearing your own voice
coming out of some machine,
you know?
Well, I guess you never
had anything but this.
So why should I?
Come on, let's get going.
You sure look frilly
to be working cattle.
I'll keep an eye on them.
Just be home before dark.
All right.
[GOATS BLEATING]
Easy now.
That's right.
[COWS MOOING]
[BIRD CRIES]
[**]
[ROOSTER CROWS]
[HORSE WHINNIES]
[SADDLE JANGLING]
Dot?
[GLASS SHATTERING]
Darling?
Get! Get!
Dot?
[**]
[HORSES SNORTING]
[HORSE STARTLES, WHINNIES]
Ah!
No!
[SCREAMING]
[SOBBING]
Dot!
Oh, Lord. Darling.
Mama, I'm cold.
I'm here, darling.
Are you all right?
I'm cold. I'm cold.
Mama, I'm cold.
Darling, where's Lilly?
Emiliano...
Yeah, I know.
Darling, where's Lilly?
Emiliano and me...
we was in the arroyo.
We heard shots from where
Brake and Lilly was.
He told me, "Stay down"...
Emiliano did.
"Don't move. Stay down."
He went to see...
but he didn't come back.
I waited like he said,
Brake was screaming, Mama.
He screamed so long
I wanted him to stop.
I know. I know it.
I know it.
Then he did.
Then someone rode away
with Lilly.
I wanted him to stop!
[SCREAMING AND SOBBING]
I know it.
Darling, did you see who?
Who took your sister?
He wore a hood.
He was Indian.
[**]
[ORGAN PLAYING]
I'm sorry
for your loss, ma'am,
but I'm afraid you got
the wrong fella in mind.
I've had the man
you're describing in jail
since last night.
Sold himself a lion's hide
and got quite a drunk on.
Unacceptable drunk.
He did say he was staying out
by your place, though.
There's been raids like this
on people here lately
in Arizona and New Mexico.
Some Apaches
jumped the reservation
at San Carlos middle
of last month sometime.
We've been getting
communications about them
near every day.
To Fort Bowie.
From me.
Possible your hostiles
attacked local ranch.
Two dead,
one girl missing.
Named...
Lilly Gilkeson.
Stop.
This takes just a moment.
The device is truly a miracle.
SALESMAN: And now you'll hear
your voice back
as clear as day.
Ladies.
WOMAN: My name's Louise Dewey.
VOICE FROM GRAPHOPHONE:
My name's Louise Dewey.
[CABLE CLICKING]
To Sheriff Purdy...
of Chloride.
Believe hostiles...
headed northwest...
toward Colorado River.
Fourth Cavalry...
will pursue...
in due course.
Well, there you have it.
I'll send the undertaker
out for the, uh...
for the remains.
You're not going after them?
Not under the present
circumstances, ma'am, no.
With the fair
being in town and all,
I need all the men
I have right here.
If you don't follow now,
their trail will get cold.
The Army is handling
the situation.
They have Apache scouts.
Takes an Apache
to catch an Apache.
If someone doesn't go now,
my daughter may be dead.
Ma'am, I am elected to keep
vigil over this town of ours.
Just one or two men, sir,
that's all I'm asking.
Ma'am, I am sorry.
Seth, I need a word with you.
DOT: It was
the Indians did it.
SALESMAN: Now, ladies,
I will not authorize
fireworks until
a water wagon is here.
SHERIFF: Ma'am, that's the
drunkard from last night.
What would you like me
to do with him?
Let him go.
I don't care.
[HORSE WHINNIES]
Mama?
Darling.
[COUGHS]
I, um, I want you to ride
over to the Handys'...
No. No, I won't.
and stay at their place
till I get back.
I'm not gonna stay behind.
I'll follow you as soon as
you're gone, you know I will.
Darling--
I'm not--
You can't leave me, Ma.
I'm going with you, Mama,
please, I am.
Now, you hear me, Dot--
I'm not staying behind.
Wherever you put me,
I'm coming after you, Ma.
You know
I'm not gonna stay put.
I swear to God,
I won't stay put.
Ssh, ssh, ssh.
Hush, hush.
Hush, now. It's all right.
[DOT SOBBING]
Hush.
The Army's headed
in the wrong direction.
17 horse tracks.
Three shod, one outrider,
two cavalry horses.
Six horses were tied
together...
carrying light loads.
Probably young women,
children.
And their captives...
those are being led along...
like packhorses.
And they're headed south.
Not north.
Probably trying to make it
to the Mexican border.
The Apaches sell
a lot of girls over there.
Top dollar.
Can you track them?
You can track them.
But if you catch them,
you'll wish you'd stayed
in that house.
I don't wanna catch them.
You just keep me
on their trail
till I get the Army down
to Fort Selden to catch them.
You wanted to give me money.
Do this instead.
[HORSE SNORTING]
[SADDLE JANGLING]
Taking this child out there
is awful foolish.
I know my daughter.
Leave her behind,
she'll just be following.
No way to care
for a young girl.
What would you know
about any of it?
I'll be just fine, thank you.
[HORSE WHINNIES]
[COW MOOS]
[**]
[SNIFFLES]
Come on, now.
[**]
MAN:
Pretty moon, Anne.
Old Bob Hadley was supposed
to stop by tonight.
God.
[CHOPPING SOUNDS]
Mama, I'm afraid in my room.
It's just your fever
giving you bad dreams, honey.
[BABY COUGHS]
You want Mama
to sing you a song?
* .Frère Jacques
Frère Jacques *
* .Dourmez vous?
Dourmez vous? *
* La la la la la
[HUMMING]
Your man didn't
keep his rifle very clean.
Well, if he wanted
to marry you, though,
I guess that's something.
He's not all bad.
Did you ever marry?
Dot's father
was my husband.
He built the ranch with me.
The notion of it was better
than the doing, I guess.
What about
the other one's father?
Didn't get much
of a look at him.
Maggie?
What you're doing,
you're doing
for your own soul.
Because what you've done,
you can't undo.
[CAMERA POWDER POPS]
You can all move now.
[INDIANS CHATTERING]
Sir, uh...
Do you suppose it's safe
for me to be on my way now?
Mister, I don't
suppose nothing.
You're theirs now.
They captured you.
Could you help me, please?
Go into the cave.
Bring picture-maker. Go!
Take them.
[BABY COUGHING]
You're heartless.
[BABY GAGGING]
PHOTOGRAPHER:
I see you gentlemen
are engaging in a little
frontier recreation out here.
ISAAC: No, these girls
are going to market.
We ain't supposed to sully
the merchandise.
I can smell him from here.
[MEN LAUGHING]
I see you share a fondness
for the photographic arts
like myself.
Where did you find
this squashed penis?
We captured him
as a gift for you.
Sir, may I have the honor
of posing you
with your captives, please?
He wants to take your picture.
Please, please.
That's perfect. Now...
very still.
Help us. Help.
Please help us.
Look your best.
Lord, protect us.
Stay behind me.
Indians.
Yeah.
But not the way
you're thinking.
Is there time enough
to give these men
a proper Christian burial?
Dead's dead,
one way or the other.
I asked if there was time.
Yeah.
There's time.
[HORSE WHINNIES]
Get in.
You must be
the pride of your people.
And you of yours.
MAN:
Prepare to dismount!
Dismount!
SOLDIER: The two on the porch
have expired, lieutenant.
Ask him why he murdered
those men in the yard.
I didn't murder anybody.
They were dead
when I got here.
What are you
doing in here?
My granddaughter
was stolen two days ago.
I trailed her to this place.
What's her name?
Uh...
You don't know your
granddaughter's name?
Well,
her sister's name is Dot.
We found two horses with
a bunch of women's property
in them.
Hang him.
SOLDIER: Other side!
There he goes!
I didn't kill anyone!
I said, I didn't kill anyone!
Come out and show your hands!
I am looking
for my granddaughter!
Then you tell me
her damn name!
I don't know her damn name!
Lilly!
Lilly Gilkeson.
You know this Indian?
He's no Indian.
Damn well looks Indian to me.
No, he's a...
That's my father.
I've been hoping
we'd find you, sir.
We need your help.
We tracked my daughter
south from Chloride.
They're heading toward Mexico.
Near as we can figure
they've hit six or seven
homesteads so far,
including this one.
Sir, Army should've
killed those heathens
when they had the chance.
They are Army, ma'am.
Deserters.
Why, I thought
they were Apache.
Apache scouts.
Formerly on
Uncle Sam's payroll.
Like Happy Jim here.
We use them to hunt down
other Apaches.
These Indians
were American soldiers?
Then a couple of months ago,
some of them turned
shot some white officers
and jumped the reservation
in San Carlos.
The 4th Cavalry started
all this by hanging
their chief.
Don't know what
they were thinking.
What makes you think
they were thinking?
This whole territory's
gone topsy-turvy.
You got Indians
running with whites,
whites running with Indians.
SOLDIER:
Get those prisoners moving!
Come on, squaw man.
Get on the way here.
Happy Jim.
You think because you're
wearing that coat
they won't put you on
the prison train to Florida
with chains on your legs?
I don't know of Florida.
It's a real swell shit-hole
of a swamp.
You'll see.
White man, you don't look like
someone who gives good advice.
[SPITS]
Break it up!
What's going on here?
I said, break it up.
I found it first,
lieutenant.
Lying bastard!
LIEUTENANT: Looks like
God intended you two to share.
Any man found looting...
will have the value
of their property
deducted from his pay.
They're enlisted men.
LIEUTENANT:
Post two men over there.
I'm going to camp
down by the river.
If I stay here long,
I might misbehave.
--right over there.
Somebody might have to
kill me.
Lieutenant?
I imagine you plan
to ride first thing.
Would it be all right
if my daughter and I
rode along with you?
Naturally,
I'm quite concerned.
Ma'am,
capturing those renegades is
the Army's highest priority.
Yes, of course.
Butcher a couple of those
goats for supper!
And I'm grateful.
But that's the assignment
of the 4th.
But the 4th is going
in the wrong direction.
I assure you,
they'll be redirected
as soon as we reach
Fort Stanton.
Stanton's three days away,
lieutenant.
My daughter will be
in Mexico by then.
Ma'am, I grieve for your
situation, I truly do.
But my assignment is to return
these hostiles in my capture
to Stanton for their prompt
and immediate deportation.
You like fish?
MAGGIE:
Go water the horses.
I watered them back at the--
I'm not asking.
Don't make them
too raw, please.
Very well, ma'am.
Lilly, she's...
not the same as Dot.
She's not strong.
She gets hurt so easy.
Sage?
What?
For the fish.
Look, I know I only
asked you to get us
as far as the the Army--
I asked you if you wanted
some sage put on your fish.
Yeah. All right.
None for Dot.
We'll ride at first light
in the morning.
If we can catch up to them,
I might have enough money
to buy her back.
If they make it to Mexico...
your child is lost.
Hey, that stuff will make you
sick, but I like it.
[SPEAKING IN APACHE]
No, no, no, no. Whoa.
That flash behind her head
bother you? It's just--
Whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa.
There's no magic.
It's an optical defect.
A flaw.
A flaw. Flaw.
Wait, wait. Hey, wait.
Look at these.
Look at these. See?
I know where all
the prettiest girls live,
from Arizona to Texas.
You pick the ones you want,
and
I'll take you right to them.
Right to their door! Look!
All the pretty girls, see?
All of them!
I'll take you-- Look!
Take your bad luck to your
grave.
What was that?
What did you just do?
ISAAC:
I'll get it done.
Uh, who of you
can skin a deer?
Hey! Who of you can skin
a deer?
Me. I can.
All right. Gotta gut her.
[SPEAKING IN APACHE]
PHOTOGRAPHER:
I can't see.
What is happening to me?
Somebody tell me.
What is happening?
I can't see.
I can't see. Please!
I can't-- Wh--
[YELLING]
[SPEAKING IN APACHE]
Hey, where's clubfoot going?
I thought we was dropping
back down into Mexico.
Seven's an unlucky number
for him.
He wants eight girls.
We go now.
Shit!
Here.
Fill the packs with meat.
I gotta take Sally. No,
I gotta take my little girl.
No! She just needs water.
She's fine.
Shut up.
She's dead now, mama.
She's my baby.
Shut up.
No!
[YELLING IN APACHE]
No! No! No!
No, no, no, no.
No!
Get up!
Trying to make a fool of me.
[SPEAKING IN APACHE]
It's gonna be all right.
I think my feet
grew two sizes today.
Try these.
They're beautiful.
They were my wife's.
My grandmother?
No.
[DOT SCREAMS]
DOT: Mama!
Mama!
MAGGIE: Dot?
You all right?
You get bit?
Did those snakes bite you?
No.
Mama, a dead man's in there.
Don't worry about that child.
Go on now.
Mama, look at his eyes.
DOT: What happened to him?
MAGGIE: He lost control
of his wagon.
Maybe he had a heart seizure.
He didn't have
a heart seizure.
His heart's in that hole.
What's behind her head?
Some people would think
it's a sign.
A good sign or bad sign?
It wasn't a very good sign for
that fella. Come here, child.
What are you doing?
These are for protection.
The man who did this
is a brujo.
A what?
It's a witch.
You need to wear one too.
You can believe in
your witchcraft
and your impiety all you want.
I believe in
what I've seen, girl.
Snakes belong on the ground.
This one hangs them
in the air.
A man's heart holds
his spirit.
This one digs it out of his
body, bleeds it out
and throws it in the dirt.
No. Don't you start this.
I know a brujo strong enough
to put an arrow in you
from one mile away.
I know a brujo who laid
his hand on a child one time.
One time.
The child cramped up,
fell down
and spit up white bees
till she died.
You stop this, you hear me?
You're scaring her.
She needs to be scared
and so do you.
Mama, please. Please.
Just on her.
[THUNDER ROLLS]
We gotta get through
that canyon before
the storm hits.
You go on and I'll follow.
Hey, give me some of
the medical stuff they stole,
the laudanum.
MAN:
You like that stuff.
ISAAC: You know,
I drink enough of this stuff,
I swear...
you start to look good to me.
Hey.
[LAUGHING]
MAN: They give this
to my grandma
when she was fixing to croak.
[DOT SCREAMING]
Mama!
I'll get her!
Catch those horses and
take them to higher ground!
I've got her!
Dot, you hold on to me!
[DOT SCREAMS]
[DOT COUGHING]
DOT: My foot's caught!
Hold your breath! Right now!
Gotta piss.
Sit up. Sshh!
I can get us out of here.
Do you hear that?
You mustn't speak.
My baby's calling me.
No. I'm sorry.
I'm so sorry.
Your baby's passed on.
No.
That's just how she sleeps.
There's nothing you can do,
so please just--
There, there. My baby.
[SNORING]
Here. Watch out while
I get the horses.
Hey, I'm just going to get
those berries I promised you.
Don't wander off.
Lord, forgive me.
[LILLY SCREAMS]
Stop squirming.
Goddamn you! Give her to me.
Get up!
No!
I got her.
Tie her legs!
Shut up!
Why?
Now we're gonna be
back to seven,
and seven's an unlucky number.
Whore! Stop!
Thank you.
Crawl.
You're better than them,
but you're not better than me.
Can she have the moccasins
now?
Yeah.
Can I just--?
I'm glad you were here.
I was bitten
by a rattlesnake.
What?
A good shaman gave me
two amulets.
Told me not to eat
rabbit meat for a year...
to say my prayers every
morning...
take care of my family,
and I might get well.
You're telling me
the only reason you came back
was because you were following
the say-so of some...
medicine man.
Is that right?
Yes. Absolutely. A rattlesnake
can make your soul...
very sick.
That's likely not
what you want to hear.
But it is the truth.
We have eight girls.
Now, we can go.
No. This one ran,
let the mother kill herself.
Go on. Hit me.
You won't fetch as many pesos
with my face all swollen,
and you know it.
This is what the rest
of your life will taste like.
Keep still.
That them?
[**]
Once they clear those trees,
they'll be riding in line
along that river.
I'll shoot the front horse.
You shoot a horse
in the middle.
We're lucky, they'll scatter.
Thought we were
gonna buy her back.
The more of them we kill
the easier they'll be
to reason with.
Maybe
she'll get clear and save us
the trouble altogether.
Dot, you keep shooting.
Try to hit a horse.
[GUN COCKS]
Mother of Jesus...
you watched your child suffer.
Give me strength.
Stop my hands from trembling.
Let them come on.
Not yet. Not yet.
Let them come.
On my call,
pick a horse in the middle
and shoot him in the neck.
I can't see Lilly.
Dot!
[CHIDIN COMMANDING IN APACHE]
[SPEAKING IN APACHE]
Take everything.
[GUNSHOTS]
[GUN COCKS]
They're Chiricahua.
Kayitah, where did you
steal that horse?
Chaa-duu-ba-its-iidan?
Hasn't someone killed you yet?
You still owe me
three lion hides, you know.
I lived with him
and his family for a time.
Good. That's good, isn't it?
Name's Kayitah.
Think the other one's his son.
Forget the hides. Give us
your horses and your guns
and we'll call it even.
They want our horses and guns.
I am not giving over
my horses.
You understand?
You'll have to kill me first.
You tell him what I said.
Now look. You pissed her off.
How can you tell? You people
look pissed off all the time.
You tell them
to get on their way.
Even better, you tell them
we want their guns
and ammunition.
Go on. You tell him.
The men you just killed
were trying to kill us too.
The witch stole
my son's future.
His bride was taken
a week ago.
He stole my granddaughter too.
We can help each other.
And she's a healer.
Ain't no undergarments
or nothing.
Dot, bring me my bag.
Go outside, sweetheart.
You don't know what diseases
these people have.
I don't usually operate
on Indians.
They have green blood and
a pinecone in their chest
instead of a heart.
Just give me that mescal.
All right. It'll hurt.
Ssh, ssh, ssh.
[SPEAKS SPANISH]
Do you still go up north
and fool around with
that fat Zuni girl?
Don't lie.
No. She started
to like me too much.
He told me...
this brujo's mother
was raped by a witch.
Came out of her womb two years
later with
a full set of teeth.
I'm not feeling
too good myself.
[KAYITAH SINGING SOFTLY]
Don't sit too close, darling.
I'm not feeling too good.
It's so cold.
It's not that cold, Ma.
[SPEAKING SOFTLY]
Hablas Español?
You knew my father?
Sí.
What do you remember
about him?
We called him
Chaa-duu-ba-its-iidan.
He was a good hunter.
Yeah. He was.
He married Laatsine.
His Chiricahua wife.
Was she beautiful?
No.
She was cross-eyed.
He was living with the Navajo
when she died of smallpox.
She died... I didn't realize.
Moved around a lot.
Never still,
Chaa-duu-ba-its-iidan.
Moving spirits
don't make happy men.
Did he love her?
His Chiricahua wife?
He loved all of them.
For a time.
Hello.
What are you doing?
I'm dreaming of what's
gonna happen tomorrow.
Can I dream on it too?
I don't know. Can you?
Can't.
Mom's talking
in her sleep again.
Sometimes at home,
she talks so loud we have
to wake her up.
Sometimes she cries.
Other times, she sounds like
somebody's hurting her.
And all the next day,
she looks at Lilly funny.
Me and Lilly notice,
even though Mama doesn't,
I don't think.
What happened to her?
I don't know,
and I wouldn't ask.
I think when she was young,
she was, um...
treated with cruelty.
She was alone in the world
at that time.
You wish you'd been there?
I don't wish.
[GROANING]
Mama.
Ma, wake up,
you're having a bad--
Don't touch her.
[CHIDIN CHANTING IN APACHE]
[MAGGIE MUTTERING]
[CHIDIN CONTINUES CHANTING]
The Brujo
has put a curse on her.
I will gather some ghost bush.
Go get your mother's Bible.
Is it bees?
Go on.
What did you leave
behind at that camp?
Today. This day,
what did you leave behind?
I don't... I don't know.
Help me again to heal.
Keep all evil away from here.
Mama. Don't let him, Mama.
[CHANTING]
"Abraham begat Isaac,
and Isaac begat Jacob.
"And Jacob begat Judas
and his brethren.
"And Judas begat Phares
and Zara of Thamar.
"And Phares begat Esrom,
and Esrom begat Aram.
"And Aram begat Aminadab,
and Aminadab begat Naasson.
"And Naasson begat Salmon,
and Salmon begat Booz
of Rachab.
"And Booz begat Obed of Ruth,
and Obed begat Jesse.
"And Jesse begat
David the king,
"and David the king begat
Solomon,
"of her that had been
the wife of Urias.
"And Solomon begat Roboam,
and Roboam begat Abia.
"And Abia begat Asa,
and Asa begat Josaphat.
"Josaphat begat Joram,
and Joram begat Ozias.
"And Ozias begat Joatham,
and Joatham begat Achaz.
"And Achaz begat Ezekias,
and Ezekias begat Manasses.
"And Manasses begat Amon,
and Amon begat Josias.
And Josias begat Jechonias
and his brethren."
[RESUMES CHANTING]
-Let's attack them.
-We don't have a chance.
Still, we must try.
Father, I can fight too.
No.
You stay here.
Morning.
Good morning.
Reckon I drank
from the wrong bottle.
Wrong as can be.
Here.
You need to keep that on.
You know, Dot was wearing hers
when she almost drowned.
Yes.
Almost.
After we attacked them,
you reckon we can still
buy them back?
I don't know.
Money's always money.
But we don't have enough
to buy them all, though.
Two or three at the most.
You get Lilly.
And get the, uh,
the Indian girl...
and...
whoever else you can.
Sorry for the rest.
I'll see you again.
Should be back by dark.
If we're not,
leave at daylight tomorrow.
That means go home.
You and Dot.
You understand?
You tell me yes,
or I'm not going.
I understand.
Kayitah...
Give this to my daughter.
She won't trust an Indian.
[**]
[SPEAKING IN APACHE]
I want to buy two girls.
I want to buy
two girls.
ISAAC: Yeah?
Do I deal with you?
No.
You deal with him, there.
You have two girls
I want to buy.
You are a make believe Indian.
Is that what you are?
Yeah, that's right.
You want to become a real
Indian? Like them?
I want to give you 600 dollars
for two girls.
Some here want your money.
For the evil
your people have done...
I want your pain.
Look at me.
Inside you are two dogs.
One is evil,
the other is good.
The mean dog fights
the good dog all the time.
Which one wins?
I don't know.
Whichever one I feed the most.
No.
They are killing each other.
That is what makes you sick.
I will make you a real Indian.
That is what your soul
asks me for.
This will tear out your soul.
[INDIANS CHATTERING,
LAUGHING]
You were born white,
but you will die an Indian.
[SPEAKING IN APACHE]
Ssh, ssh!
Do you know this?
I don't understand.
Die slow.
The vultures will
eat your guts while you watch.
Please. Please.
That's my mother's.
What did you do to my mother?
What did you do?
[LILLY SCREAMS]
[KAYITAH YELLS]
[SPITS]
You killed him.
You killed us all.
There is nothing we can do.
There is no hope.
[BIRD SQUAWKS]
My friend.
Do a favor for me.
Forget your gophers and mice.
Take me to my family.
[BIRD CRIES]
MAGGIE: Give them repentance
and better minds.
Be merciful, O God, to those
who are in any trouble.
And do thou,
O God of pity,
administer to them
according to their...
Ma?
MAGGIE: ...needs.
Grandpa said we was to leave
in the morning.
He'll come back.
He's gonna come back.
Reward all those
who have done us good.
Pardon all those
who have done or wish us evil.
Give them repentance
and better minds.
Be merciful, O God, to anyone
who's in any trouble.
And deal with them,
O God of pity,
according to their needs
with kindness, just as
Jesus Christ, your son, did.
I told you to go home.
How bad are you hurt?
I've seen the girl.
She's still alive.
Your father never stopped
fighting.
They killed him like cowards.
Are we gonna go get Lilly?
You can raise this child.
Take her home.
And you can be sure of that.
You do anything else,
you're likely to lose two
daughters and your own life.
I don't know
how to leave her.
You can't turn away from that?
Can you?
All right...
Magdalena.
All right.
You.
You scared of dead things?
[SPEAKS IN APACHE]
They finally
going to get buyers?
He'll be back.
We sell them today.
ISAAC: Hey, my friend,
we're getting paid today.
The body is gone.
It's him, look!
He's come back from the dead!
Don't think like that.
Come this way with me.
It's a trick, you idiots!
Get the girl.
Get down there.
[SPEAKS IN APACHE]
Mama.
I'm sorry. I'm sorry.
I'm sorry.
It's all right, baby.
It's all right.
[GUNSHOT]
You cut them loose.
Get to the horses!
I thought we killed that
bastard.
Get going!
Get out of here, Maggie.
Hyah!
[WHISTLES]
[SPEAKING IN APACHE]
Where are the women?
Give me your horses.
I will bring them back
before nightfall.
And leave us here
with no horses?
[LAUGHING]
[MOCKING LAUGH]
We don't have time
to drink water. Let's go!
Can they catch us?
Oh, yeah.
Help me.
MAGGIE: Take my arm.
I got her.
We're going to the top!
If your horse quits,
get off and go on afoot!
Hold on to the tail.
I got you.
You knew this was here.
I've had occasion
to use it before.
We'll never make it over to
the other side before dark.
We'll have to last out
the night right here.
Put as much dry brush
as you can carry in this gap!
Are you all right?
Your hair's all tangled.
Here, let me get it.
[SOBBING]
It's all right.
It's all right, Lill-Lill.
You'll see.
I dreamed on it.
We're gonna get away,
and Grandpa's gonna
come live with us
and we're all
gonna be a family.
You'll see.
Right, Ma?
Isn't that right?
Yeah.
[CHIDIN CHANTING]
[HORSE WHINNIES]
[GUN CLICKS]
Chaa-duu-ba-its-iidan.
You know that Indian name
of yours?
What's that mean?
Very hard to translate that.
Try it.
It means "shit for luck."
Is that right?
Yes, it is.
Chiricahua value family
very highly.
A man doesn't live
with his wife and children,
he's not considered
particularly...
enviable.
I don't have any Indian...
brothers or sisters?
None that lived.
What did you see in them...
you didn't see in us?
Why didn't you stay?
There's an Apache story
about a man
that woke up one morning
and saw a hawk on the wind.
Walked outside
and never returned.
After he died, he met his wife
in the spirit world.
She asked him why
he never came home.
He said, "Well,
the hawk kept flying."
There's always the next
something, Maggie.
And that will take a man away.
You tell yourself
you're protecting them,
they're better off
without you.
Stay or go, there's
nothing a man can do
to protect his family
from himself.
I guess I do realize now
I made people's lives more...
difficult by the things
I have done...
and the things
I have not done.
People I did love, mostly.
I'm not forgiving you.
Not asking you to.
[OBJECT LANDS WITH A CLINK]
I wore that birthing
both my girls.
I thought I'd die wearing it.
I've always liked this thing.
Your mother gave it to me.
Never meant to
leave it behind.
Thank you.
I better see
to Lilly and them.
[WOMAN SCREAMS]
[BULLET RICOCHETS]
Look out!
[HORSE WHINNIES]
Pull those horses back!
Your brujo's dead!
Muerto!
Fuera!
Leave!
[SPEAKING IN APACHE]
[**]
[BIRD CHIRPS]
MAGGIE: Let's go home.
[**]